听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
接下来 我们将要学习
Next, let's have a look at
实现不同广播模型的具体算法
algorithms for actually implementing these different models of broadcast.
我们将分两个步骤来讲解
So, we're going to do that in two separate stages.
首先 我们将展示如何让尽力广播变为可靠广播
First of all, we'll show how to take best-effort broadcast and make it reliable.
一旦我们有了可靠广播
And then, once we've got reliable broadcast,
我们就可以将可靠广播作为基础层 在此之上构建顺序传递模块
we can layer on top of that modules for doing the delivery order,
从而允许我们实现FIFO广播、因果关系广播、以及全序关系广播
which allows us then to do either FIFO or causal or total order broadcast.
我们先从可靠层开始
So, let's start with the reliability layer here.
你可能觉得 最显然的一种广播算法实现方法是
The most obvious thing you might think about as a broadcast algorithm is
你想让一个节点广播一条消息
you have the node that wants to broadcast a message
只需要让将此条消息通过点对点链路发送给所有其他的节点
just sends that message individually to every other node via point-to-point links
并保证点对点链路是可靠链路
and make those point-to-point links reliable
如果消息在发送过程中丢失 发送者只需要重新发送消息
so that if the message gets dropped along the way, then the sender will resend it,
这样一来 通过重传机制
and so, because then through the retransmission,
消息最终都可以成功传输到所有其他节点
the message will eventually get through to every other node.
不幸的是 这种方法不可行 原因是可能会发生下面这种情况
This unfortunately does not quite work because what could happen is this here,
A尝试向B和C广播消息m_1
A could try to broadcast message m_1 to B and C,
消息被成功传输到C处 但消息在传输到B的过程中丢失了
the message gets through to C, but the message gets dropped on its way to B.
因此 A要向B重传消息
So, A has to retransmit the message to B,
但随后 A在完成消息重传前崩溃了
but then A crashes before A is able to complete this retransmission.
在这种情况下 没有人能够向B重传消息m_1
And in this case, nobody is ever going to retry the sending of message m_1 to B.
因此 C将传递一条B无法传递的消息
And so, therefore, C will have delivered a message that B did not deliver.
B永远无法传递此条消息
B is never going to deliver this message.
此时 节点间出现了不一致的情况
And therefore, we have an inconsistency.
我们现在需要设计一个健壮算法
So, we have to now design an algorithm which is robust
使得即使消息发送方崩溃了
so that even if the sender of a message crashes,
所有剩余的节点仍然可以就实际传递的消息达成一致
all of the remaining nodes will still agree on which message was actually delivered.
我们可以使用的一种技术称为迫切可靠广播
And so, one technique we can use is called eager reliable broadcast,
此技术本质上是让每个人向每个地方都发送消息
and that relies on essentially just everybody sending messages everywhere.
首先 A向B和C广播m_1
So, first of all, A wants to broadcast m_1 to B and C.
当B先收到m_1时
When B first receives m_1,
B通过点对点链路向其他每个节点重广播此条消息
it rebroadcasts the same message again via point-to-point links to every other node.
这样一来 即使A崩溃了 B仍然可以进一步传播消息
And so, this way, then even if A crashed, B will have further disseminated the message.
当C先收到消息时
And when C first receives the message,
C同样也向其他所有人重广播此条消息
C will also rebroadcast the message to everyone else.
此算法确实能保证可靠性
And so, this algorithm actually does ensure reliability.
此算法可以保证 即使有节点崩溃 所有未崩溃节点仍然可以收到消息
It ensures that even if nodes crash, all of the non-crashed nodes receive the message.
然而 这个算法的开销极大 因为每个收到消息的节点
However, it is quite expensive, because every node that receives a message
都将再次将此条消息发送给其他n-1个节点
will again send that message to n-1 other nodes.
总的来说 每当一个节点想要广播一条消息时
And so, in total, we're going to end up with O(n^2) messages being sent
此协议最终都需要发送O(n^2)条消息
for every single message that a node wants to broadcast.
我们得到了可靠性 但代价是消耗了相当高的网络带宽
So, we get reliability, but at the cost of fairly high network bandwidth.
为此 人们设计了很多不同的优化算法
Now, lots of different algorithms have been designed to optimize this.
一组特别有趣的算法叫流言协议
And one particular interesting group of algorithms are called gossip protocols.
此类协议模仿了流言在人际网络中的传播方式
So, they are modeled in the way how gossip might spread through a network of people,
一个人从别人那里听到流言蜚语
where one person hears gossip from somebody,
他们把这些流言告诉了其他人
and they then tell a few other people about this gossip,
最终
and so eventually,
流言在群组/群体中完成了传播
this information spreads through a group, through a population of people.
有时也把这类协议称为传染病协议
And they're sometimes also called epidemic protocols,
因为此类协议的消息传播方式
because they're somewhat similar to the way that
与传染病在人群中的传播方式很相似
an infectious disease might spread through a population.
在这个例子中 每一个小黑点都代表系统中的一个节点
And so, in this example here each little blob is a node in the system.
我们已经为算法选择好了参数
And I've just taken as the parameter for this algorithm that
每个节点会向其他3个节点发送消息
each node sends on the message to 3 other nodes.
这3个节点是随机选取的
And those 3 other nodes are picked at random.
因此 这里的红色节点将消息发送给其他3个节点
And so, here, the red node is sending the message to 3 other nodes.
这3个节点收到消息后
And then, these 3 other nodes each receive the message
再随机选择3个节点 并将消息重广播给这3个节点
and they each rebroadcast the message to 3 other randomly selected nodes.
收到广播消息的接收方再将消息广播给其他节点
And those recipients of those broadcasts, they again broadcast them further to others.
你可以看到
And you see that
消息有时会被发送给之前已经接收过消息的节点
sometimes, messages go to a node that has already received a message previously.
消息有时甚至会回传给
Sometimes, messages even go back to a node
过去某个时间拥有该消息的节点
that had the message sometime in the past.
但最终 此协议执行几轮之后
But eventually, over several rounds of this protocol,
有很高的概率
there with very high probability, we reach a stage
能使所有节点都收到了消息
in which the message has received all of the nodes,
所有节点都变成了黑色
and now all of the nodes are black.
我们再来看一遍这个动画 这个动画做得太漂亮了
Let me just go through that animation again because it's so beautiful.
我们可以看到 消息在节点中不断传播
So, we have the node spreading. There is the message spreading here.
此时
And so, in this case,
在本例中 经过6轮通信
all 30 nodes in this example have received the message
所有30个节点都收到了消息
after about 6 rounds of communication.
我们可以调整流言协议中的很多参数
So, there are lots of details that you can tune about gossip protocols
例如 节点如何决定
about how exactly they decide
什么时候发送消息、什么时候停止发送消息
when to send messages and when to stop sending messages and so on.
但协议的基本原理就是这样
But the basic principle is this.
这是可靠广播的一种实现方法
They are a way of achieving reliable broadcasts.
此方法非常健壮
And they are quite robust
即使部分节点崩溃 部分消息在网络传输中丢失
so that even if some of the nodes crash or some of the messages get lost in the network,
我们也有很高的概率
we still have very high probability that
使所有节点均成功收到消息
all of the messages get through to all of the nodes.
我们现在得到了可靠性
OK, so, that gives us the reliability.
接下来 我们考虑传递顺序
Now, next let's look at the ordering.
例如 如果我们想获得FIFO广播
So, if we want to achieve FIFO broadcasts, for example,
这意味着我们必须保证
that means we have to ensure that
相同发送方发送的所有消息均要按照正确的顺序传递
all of the messages by the same sender are delivered in the right order.
这是一个实现此顺序传递的算法
This is an algorithm of how we might achieve this.
每个节点要维护三个变量
So, each node here maintains three variables,
发送方顺序号（sendSeq）是一个整数
sender sequence number (sendSeq) is just an integer
每当此节点广播一条消息时 此顺序号会递增
that gets incremented for every message broadcast by this particular node,
已传递（delivered）是一个整数向量
delivered is a vector of integers
表示我们已经传递了来自每个特定发送方的消息数量
indicating how many messages from each particular sender we have delivered,
缓冲区（buffer）是消息保留队列
and buffer is a holdback queue of messages so that
如果一条消息未准备好被传递 我们就将此消息放在缓冲区中
if a message is not yet ready to be delivered, we put it in the buffer,
后续某个时刻再从缓冲区中取出这条消息
and then pick it out of the buffer sometime later.
如果我们想广播一条消息
So, if we want to broadcast a message,
我们在消息上附加发送方i的节点号
we attached the node number of the sender i,
再在消息上附加发送方顺序号
and we attach the sequence number of the sender to the message,
通过可靠广播将此三元组传播给所有节点
and this triple gets disseminated to all of the nodes via reliable broadcast.
随后 我们将递增发送方顺序号 为下一次广播做准备
And then, we increment the sequence number for next time we want to broadcast.
当节点N_i通过可靠网络收到一条消息时
Also, when we receive a message via a reliable broadcast at node N_i,
我们首先将消息放置到缓冲区
we first of all add the message to the buffer,
随后 我们查看缓冲区 尝试获取已经准备好传递的所有消息
and then, we look at the buffer trying to find any messages that are ready to be delivered.
这里的“准备好传递”是指
And here, ready to be delivered means that
对于任意给定发送方 我们能在缓冲区找到一条消息
for any given sender, we have a message in the buffer
此消息的顺序号刚好等于
where the sequence number is the next integer that we are expecting
此特定发送方广播消息所拥有的下一个顺序号
in the sequence of sequence number from that particular sender.
如果有一条消息与我们期望的顺序号相匹配
And so, if we have a message matching that,
我们就把这条消息取出来 传递给应用
then we take that message, deliver it to the application,
随后 我们找到表示各发送方已传递消息数量的本地向量
and we increment our local vector of the number of messages we have delivered
增加此特定发送方对应位置的计数值
from a particular sender.
这个协议可以让我们得到FIFO广播
And so, this is it. This achieves FIFO broadcast.
接下来 我们来看看因果关系广播
Next, let's have a look at causal broadcast.
算法结构非常相似
The structure of the algorithm is very similar.
我们仍然从3个变量开始
We start with the same 3 variables.
同样地 我们有发送方顺序号（sendSeq）
So, again, we have a sender sequence number (sendSeq),
我们有一个记录已传递消息数量的向量（delivered）
we have a vector counting the number of delivered messages (delivered),
我们有保留缓冲区（buffer）
and we have the holdback buffer (buffer).
当N_i想广播一条消息时
When we want to broadcast a message at N_i,
首先 我们创建一个名为“依赖”（deps）的新变量
first of all, we create this new variable deps.
此变量描述了消息的因果依赖关系
So, that captures the causal dependencies of this message.
我们用这个变量决定哪条消息在这条消息之前发生
So, it's a way of determining which messages happened before this particular message.
在广播这条消息之前
And those will have to be then
所有之前发生的消息都需要先完成传递
all of the messages that have to be delivered before this message being broadcast.
我们将已传递消息数量向量拷贝到deps中
So, we take deps to be a copy of our delivered vector.
我们将deps中广播节点所对应位置的元素更新为发送方顺序号
And we update the broadcasting node's own entry to be equal to the sendSeq.
随后 我们仍然通过可靠广播发送此条消息
And then, we send the message via reliable broadcast again.
此时 我们不在消息上附加顺序号了
This time, we don't attach the sequence number,
我们附加这个依赖向量 以及表示节点索引值的i
but we attach this dependencies vector, in addition to i, which is the index of the node.
随后 我们和之前一样 递增发送方顺序号
And then, we increment the sender sequence number as before.
此时 我们在得到的消息上
OK, so, this time, we've got messages
附加了一个向量 而不是一个单独的整数了
that have a vector attached to them, rather than a single integer.
当一个节点收到其中一条消息时
When one of these messages gets delivered at a node,
我们首先和之前一样 将消息放置在缓冲区中
we first of all put the message in the buffer as usual.
现在 我们搜索准备好传递的消息
And now, we search for any messages that are ready to be delivered.
即搜索所有满足因果依赖关系的消息
And these are any messages whose causal dependencies have been satisfied.
对于所有与当前消息存在因果关系的广播消息
So, any messages that were broadcast before the current message,
本地节点都需要先完成传递
they have already been delivered by the local node.
如果一个消息满足上述条件 则此条消息已经准备好被传递了
If those have been delivered, then this message is ready to be delivered
因为所有满足因果依赖关系的消息都已经被传递了
because its causal dependencies have already been delivered.
我们在缓冲区中遍历所有消息的依赖向量
So, here we search for any sender dependencies and message in the buffer
找到依赖向量小于等于当前依赖向量的消息
such that the dependencies vector is less than or equal to the delivered vector.
这里的≤操作符
And this ≤ operator
就是我们稍早前在向量时钟里定义的≤操作符
is exactly the ≤ operator that we defined on vector clocks a little while back.
虽然这个算法与向量时钟算法不完全一样
So, even though this algorithm is not exactly the same as the vector clocks algorithm,
但此算法中的整数向量使用方法和向量时钟里的用法很相似
it's similar in the way that it does use these vectors of numbers,
这个算法也使用≤操作符来比较依赖向量 从而实现因果关系广播
and it uses this ≤ comparison as a part of its algorithm for causal broadcast.
如果我们找到了满足因果依赖关系的消息 我们就传递这条消息
If we have a message that satisfies the dependencies, we deliver it,
我们从缓冲区移除这条消息
we remove the message from the buffer,
我们增加此特定发送方的已传递消息数量
and we increment the number of messages we have delivered from that particular sender.
此算法可以实现因果关系广播
And this ensures causal broadcast.
你可能需要花点时间想一想
You might have to think about the algorithm for a little bit
让自己信服这个算法是正确的
to convince yourself that it really is correct,
但我认为这个算法确实是正确的
but I think it is correct.
这就是因果关系广播
So, that is causal broadcast.
最后是全序关系广播
Finally, total order broadcast.
全序关系广播有一点难
So, total order broadcast is a bit harder, so, because remember,
我们需要协商消息的全序关系
we have to somehow agree on what this total order is of messages
这样才能确定消息的传递顺序
in which order the messages are going to get delivered.
我们来看一个简单实现此目的的算法
Let's say one simple way of doing this.
我们把其中一个节点选为主节点
We're going to pick one of the nodes as the leader.
主节点将负责
And this leader is going to be in charge of
决定消息传递的顺序
determining the order in which the messages get delivered.
这也是有时会把主节点称为定序节点的原因
So, that's why it's also sometimes known as a sequencer,
因为此节点会决定消息的顺序
because it sequences the messages.
如果一个节点想要广播一条消息
And if one node wants to broadcast a message,
它并不直接向其他节点广播这条消息
it doesn't directly broadcast it to the other nodes.
此节点需要通过FIFO链路向主节点发送此条消息
Instead, the node sends it to the leader via a FIFO link probably.
主节点随后通过FIFO广播向全组广播此条消息
And the leader then broadcast it by a FIFO broadcast to the entire group.
由于所有的消息都会由主节点发送
And so, because all of the messages are going through the leader,
因此 主节点广播消息的顺序
simply the order in which the leader broadcasts the messages then
就是其他所有节点传递消息的顺序
is the order in which all of the other nodes will deliver the messages,
这是因为主节点会使用FIFO广播来发送消息
since we're talking about FIFO broadcast here.
这个协议效果良好
And this works quite nicely.
只存在一个问题
It just has the problem that
如果主节点崩溃了 广播机制就无法再传递任何消息
if our leader crashes, then no more messages can get delivered,
因为我们要求所有消息都通过主节点发送
because we're requiring all of our messages to go through the leader.
因此 我们需要一种方法
So, really, we would need some kind of way of
将主节点从一个节点换为另一个节点 以防止主节点崩溃
changing the leader from one node to another in case that leader crashes.
但安全的实现这一点是很困难的
But this is quite difficult to do safely,
因为如果系统最后产生了两个不同的主节点
because if you end up with two different leaders,
我们就无法保证消息的全序关系了
then your guarantee of total order is gone.
我们后续介绍共识协议时
So, we will see ways of actually doing this kind of leader change safely
再介绍安全更换主节点的方法
in a later lecture when we'd come to talk about consensus.
现在 我们把这个问题留作一个公开问题
But for now, I'm just going to leave this as an open problem.
还有一种实现全序关系广播的方法
There's another way you could achieve total order broadcast,
此方法不需要依赖主节点
which does not rely on a leader.
你需要依赖的是Lamport时钟
Instead, you could rely on Lamport clocks.
回忆一下 Lamport时钟生成了一个全序关系
So, remember, Lamport timestamps have an associated total order.
我们可以把这个全序关系
And we can use that total order
作为传递消息的顺序
as the order in which we are going to deliver the messages.
我们在每条消息上附加一个Lamport时间戳
So, we attach a Lamport timestamp to every message.
我们按照前面讨论的方法创建Lamport时间戳
We create those Lamport timestamps in the usual way like we have discussed,
随后 通过可靠广播来广播消息
and then, broadcast those messages via some kind of reliable broadcast.
接下来 每个节点都需要保证
And then, each node needs to ensure that
节点按照Lamport时间戳递增的顺序传递消息
it delivers messages in increasing order of their Lamport timestamps.
这是可行的 但是这个算法依赖一个特定的知识
And this works, but it does rely on one particular piece of knowledge
当节点传递一条消息时 它需要确定
which is at the time when a node delivers a message, it needs to be sure that
后续所有消息的Lamport时间戳
there will be no future messages with a Lamport timestamp
不会小于其将要传递消息所关联的时间戳
less than this message that it's about to deliver,
因为如果此节点传递了此条消息
because if it did deliver the message now,
随后 节点收到了一条时间戳更小的消息
and then later, a message with a lower timestamp arrives,
这就意味着此节点按照错误的顺序传递了消息
then it would have delivered them in the wrong order,
因为每个节点都必须严格按照Lamport时间戳递增的顺序传递消息
because it has to deliver the messages in strictly ascending order of Lamport timestamp.
因此 我们需要通过一种方法知道
So, therefore, we need some way of knowing that
后续消息的时间戳
there will not be any future messages
不会小于某个特定的阈值
with a timestamp less than some particular threshold.
这是有可能做到的
And it is possible to know that,
因为如果节点之间通过FIFO链路通信 那么我们实际上知道
because if we use FIFO links between the nodes, then actually, we know that
每个节点会按照Lamport时间戳递增的顺序发送消息
each node will send messages in increasing order of Lamport timestamp,
我们也会按照递增顺序收到这些消息
and we receive those messages in increasing order.
因此 如果我们能收到所有其他节点的消息
So, therefore, if we've heard from every other node,
那么我们就能知道
then we know that the minimum timestamp
其他所有节点发送消息的最小时间戳
that we've seen across any of the other nodes
就是我们能得到的最小时间戳
is going to be the minimum we're ever going to see.
后续不可能收到此时间戳更小的时间戳了
So, there will never be any later timestamps than this one.
基于此方法 我们就有可能构建出全序关系广播
And so, based on that, it is now possible to again create total order broadcast.
不幸的是 此方法同样无法容错
Again, unfortunately, this approach is not fault-tolerant,
因为在这种情况下
because in this case,
如果其中一个节点崩溃 这个节点就不会再发送任何消息
if just one of the nodes crashes, it will not be sending any more messages.
Lamport时间戳也就不会再向前移动
So, the Lamport timestamps won't be moving forward anymore.
因此 节点也不会再传递任何消息
And so, no messages get delivered anymore.
这两个算法都可以运行 但两个算法都无法容错
So, these two algorithms do work, but neither of them is fault-tolerant.
在后面的课程中
And in a later lecture,
我们将学习如何实现可容错的全序广播
we will see ways of achieving total order broadcast in a way that is fault-tolerant.